Okay, בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is קע"ה, kuf ayin
hey, בבא בתרא Bava Batra 175, the penultimate דף. daf. And we
pick up with the on קע"ד עמוד ב', kuf ayin dalet amud
bet, 174b, about a third of the way down. And
we
are dealing with רבן שמעון בן גמליאל's Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel statement
in the משנה mishna after we've discussed the liability of an ערב
areiv and whether the responsibility and that they go to him after
you go to the לווה. loveh. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel says that if somebody is an ערב areiv for כתובה,
ketubah, which means basically he's guaranteeing the husband's responsibility, so that if
there's divorce or death, the wife can collect. If she can't collect
from the husband's estate, she can collect from the ערב. areiv. That,
and then they get divorced, that basically you have to insist that
the man makes a נדר neder not to remarry his wife, because
we're concerned that there's going to be some type of a scheme
in place and he and his wife are in cahoots and they're
going to use this to collect from the ערב areiv and then
they'll get remarried. Okay, and nobody really disagrees on that ruling in
the משנה. mishna. So let's see what the גמרא gemara says. It
says, משה בר עצרי, Moshe bar Atzri, so this person משה בר
עצרי, Moshe bar Atzri, ערבא דכתובתה דכלתה הוה. areva deketubata dekallatei havah.
He was the guarantor of his daughter-in-law's כתובה, ketubah, meaning it would
have been more, maybe, straightforward to say he was the guarantor for
his son's debt, for his son's assumption of responsibility in the כתובה
ketubah for his daughter-in-law,
for his son's wife. So, רב הונא בריה, Rav Huna brei, now
רב הונא Rav Huna was the son of this משה בר עצרי.
Moshe bar Atzri. צורבא מרבנן הוה. tzoreba meirabanan havah.
So he was, you know, a תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. ודחיקא ליה
מילתא, vedachika lei milta, and he was having a hard time financially.
He really couldn't get a good פרנסה, parnassah, put food on the
table. אמר אביי, amar Abaye, so אביי Abaye said, לימא ליה דליסב
עצה לרב הונא דליגרשה לדביתיה ותיזיל ותיגבי כתובתה מאבוה. leima lei deliseiv
eitzah leRav Huna deligarshei lediveiteih veteizei vetigbei ketubatah mei-avuha. So he said,
אביי Abaye said, isn't there anybody around that might can go and
advise רב הונא Rav Huna that what he should do is divorce
his wife and then she can go collect her כתובה ketubah from
his father, means his father, and from the guarantor. והדר ניהדרה, ve-hadar
neihaderah, and then he can remarry her. So we have a perfect,
somebody should, like אביי Abaye was sort of not taking responsibility, he
wasn't going to be the one to advise, but he was dropping
a broad hint that somebody should go and give him this advice.
Now this seems very troubling that that would be how you would
advise somebody. And let's see what the גמרא gemara says with this.
אמר ליה רבא, amar lei Rava, so רבא Rava said to him,
והדירנה הנאה תנן, vehayadirana hana'ah tanan, but רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel says in the משנה mishna that he would have
to make a נדר neder not to get הנאה hana'ah from her
to prevent himself from remarrying her. So it's not going to work
anyway. So it's funny that, you know, רבא Rava is concerned with
practically it wouldn't work, not that there was anything wrong with this
idea.
אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye said back to
him,
אטו כל דמגרש בבי דינא מגרש? atu kol degaresh bevei dina garesh?
What, everybody who divorces his wife does it in a בית דין?
beit din? Let him divorce his wife and then who's to say
that it'll be a public matter? I mean, now of course you
wouldn't even think about doing it without a בית דין, beit din,
but who's to say that it'll be a public matter? And therefore,
who's going to enforce this idea that he has to make this
נדר? neder? So this is like very, very disturbing. First of all,
you know, if that's the הלכה halakha that you're supposed to be
ידירנה הנאה, yadirana hana'ah, then even if there is no בית דין,
beit din, shouldn't that be how you're acting? What, it should be
the בית דין's beit din responsibility and not like your responsibility to
do this? Number two, probably even more troubling is that, you know,
if רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel wants you to
make this this נדר, neder, then it's obviously saying that there is
something morally wrong with this decision. I mean, you would know that
even without רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. You know,
you're doing this whole scheme to get money from the ערב areiv
who did you this favor and was the guarantor of your loan
and you're not really planning on divorcing your wife. So there seems
to be, okay, technically he's legally liable, technically you are divorced, but
you know, it's like really, that's what we should be doing is
just technically? Like this seems like, this seems deeply disturbing on many
levels. Let's let's see what the גמרא gemara does. To some degree
the גמרא gemara asks this question. Okay, so the גמרא gemara says
like this, וסוף איגלאי מילתא דכהן הוא. vesof iglaei milta dekahan hu.
In the end it turned out that anyway that this רב הונא
Rav Huna the son of of משה בר עצרי Moshe bar Atzri
was a כהן. kohen. So if he were to divorce his wife,
he wouldn't be able to remarry her. So even were he to
follow אביי's Abaye advice, he would get stuck. It wasn't exactly clear
whether that was found out before or after he divorced. Hopefully it
was before he divorced his wife. אמר אביי, amar Abaye, so אביי
Abaye said, היינו דאמרי אינשי בתר עניא אזלא עניותא, hainei de-amri inshi
batar aniya azla aniyuta, poverty follows the poor. The poor get poorer.
You know, oh, this guy, he just has bad luck after bad
luck. Okay, even this advice that I wanted to help him, it
isn't, it's not going to help him, he's really stuck. Okay. מי
אמר אביי הכי Mi amar Abaye hachi now we're going to ask
how אביי Abaye could make such a
suggestion. והאמר אביי Veha amar Abaye doesn't אביי Abaye say איזהו רשע
ערום זה המשיא עצה למכור בנכסיו כרבן שמעון בן גמליאל? Eizehu rasha
arum zeh masi etza limchor binichasav k'rabban Shimon ben Gamliel? This is
a completely different רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, who
it's considered to be a wicked person who
is scheming or but ערום arum could also mean like clever, he's
successful, but he's doing something bad. This would be somebody who gives
somebody an advice. The הלכה halacha is that if I give a
gift to ראובן Reuven and I say this field should be yours
ואחריך לשמעון v'acharecha l'Shimon and after you die it should go on
to שמעון, Shimon, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says
if ראובן Reuven were to sell it to a third party to
לוי, Levi, then it would not go to
שמעון. Shimon. So that would be sort of like smart for ראובן
Reuven because ראובן Reuven only has the use of the field while
ראובן Reuven is still alive. If he goes ahead and he sells
it to לוי, Levi, לוי Levi now gets the field permanently. So
the field is worth more to לוי Levi than it is to
ראובן Reuven because ראובן Reuven breaks sort of the progression of it
going from him to שמעון. Shimon. So if somebody else were to
come and say to ראובן, Reuven, hey ראובן, Reuven, you'd be better
off selling this field to לוי, Levi, getting the full value of
the field and then you'd be better off with having it just
now that you have it just to use for while you're alive.
So ראובן Reuven would be totally within his rights to do that.
But if somebody gives that advice, they basically are getting involved, this
is why you're a רשע rasha because you're getting involved in a
ריב לא לו. riv lo lo. It's not your issue at all
and here you are, you're interfering in something that's none of your
business and you are benefiting ראובן Reuven at the expense of שמעון
Shimon and against the wishes of the person who gave this field
to ראובן, Reuven, against my wishes. So you're subverting my wishes to
benefit somebody when you have no interest in it at somebody else's
expense. So you should not be doing things like that even if
technically legally it's acceptable. So here too, אביי Abaye is suggesting that
somebody is getting involved in something that's not his business and he's
going ahead and trying to give advice to
this רב הונא Rav Huna that he should do something which is
against the whole intent of the
ערב areiv and is really hurting the
ערב areiv through this whole deception. So how could you be doing
such a thing? How could this be morally acceptable? So let's take
a look. Even if it's going to be technically legally playing by
the rules. So the גמרא Gemara says בנו שאני וצורבא מרבנן שאני.
Bino shani v'tzurba m'rabbanan shani. No, here
it's not so bad. In the end, who is this רב הונא
Rav Huna going to collect from? He's going to collect from his
father, this משה בר אטרי. Moshe bar Atri. The father is the
guarantor for the כתובה. ketubah. So maybe the father doesn't want to
just give his son a loan, maybe the son is even embarrassed
to ask for a loan or doesn't want to give his son
a gift. But at the end of the day, you're not taking
money out of a family. In the end you're passing money from
the father to the son. So
like
in this case it's not
you're not taking it from ראובן Reuven and giving it to שמעון
Shimon like in the case of the field to a total stranger
and you're
cheating the intent of the giver. Here you're taking it from a
father and giving it to a son.
But still that wasn't why the father agreed to be the guarantor
ערב. areiv. I mean maybe the father doesn't mind so much, but
maybe he does. So that's not so satisfying that it's like, oh
it's not so bad, it's still just going from father to son.
That's answer number one.
And point number two anyway is that even if that wasn't as
much of a diversion of the resources, of the property, of the
money, this case is much more of a deception. In the case
of selling the field, ראובן Reuven is entitled, he might not know
the law, he might not be aware that he's entitled, it might
not be exactly what the gifter wanted to do, but there's no
deception. He's just pursuing his self-interest. Here the whole thing is deceitful.
So it's very disturbing that the גמרא Gemara sort of makes its
peace with it. I mean it's making its peace with it because
אביי Abaye said it. But let's see also the other thing it
adds. So number one the גמרא Gemara says בנו שאני
וצורבא מרבנן שאני. Bino shani v'tzurba m'rabbanan shani.
It's also different because this רב הונא Rav Huna was a תלמיד
חכם. talmid chacham. So if it's a תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, what's
the point? The point is you're allowed to cheat if it's for
the sake of תורה? Torah? That's a really bad message. Maybe the
point is that it wasn't considered to be not his issue, like
something that was none of his business. It is the business to
try to make sure that תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim can put food
on the table. Okay fine, so you're trying to. weren't interfering in
something that you had no business interfering in. But again, none of
this really addresses the issue about the deception. So this really remains,
I would say, quite problematic. All right, now but whatever, that's where
the גמרא Gemara ends up. Let's continue. So now the גמרא Gemara
says like this.
והא ערב הוא, v'ha areiv hu, one minute, how could the father
anyway be on the hook for the כתובה? ketubah? He was an
ערב, areiv, וקיימא לן ערב דכתובה לא משתעבד. v'kayma lan areiv d'ketubah
lo mishtabed. And we have a principle, which we're about to say
in a few lines, that an ערב areiv of a כתובה ketubah
does not really legally liable. Why is he not really legally liable?
Because as we'll see, the reason a person would be a guarantor
to sign on for a כתובה ketubah would be to help the
couple get married. But it doesn't really mean and it's not like
a loan where the person borrows money then really owns it and
you're trying to make sure that the lender gets his money back.
Here no loan is taking place and the person is doing it
just to ensure that the couple get married, so he's not really
serious about his commitment, which is obviously which is also disturbing because
it might be true that no money is lent, but the woman
is making a decision right to commit her life to this man
and one of the things that חז״ל Chazal instituted the כתובה ketubah
was to make sure that her interests were protected. So she's not
giving over any money, but she's sort of giving over herself. And
if it's important that her interest be protected, it's important that they
be protected. So you know, that's disturbing, but it's not that the
גמרא Gemara says that it's not important that she have the כתובה.
ketubah. What it's more saying is is that this man probably who
decided to be an ערב areiv wasn't being serious about it. We
can't assume he's being serious about it. Again, it's still a bit
of a problem that the halakhic system reinforces that rather than demands
that he actually does keep by his commitment. But the assumption here
is you have to go by גמר דעת g'mar da'at and the
guy was just throwing it out there to make moves things along
with the wedding, not being serious. Okay, now that says the גמרא
Gemara says is how we rule, which is quite fascinating because it's
exactly against our משנה Mishnah where רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel absolutely assumes that an ערב areiv is liable, which why
he demands to make this vow that you're not going to get,
you know, remarried, you're not going to get any הנאה. hana'ah. Okay,
but the גמרא Gemara doesn't try to reconcile it with the משנה,
Mishnah, just says we rule that there is that you really do
not assume this responsibility. So then why in this case did this
ערב areiv have that responsibility? והא קיימא לן, v'ha kayma lan, the
גמרא Gemara says, ערב דכתובה לא משתעבד, areiv d'ketubah lo mishtabed, that
he really does not become encumbered, does not become obligated. קבלן הוה.
kablan havah. Oh, he wasn't just an ערב, areiv, he was a
קבלן, kablan, which we said yesterday, means that he didn't just say
I'll be the guarantor, he said it is like I am receiving
the money, I will pay the money. Here there's no money to
receive, but it's like the debt comes directly to me and I
will pay it. Okay, so in that case,
that's why it would work even in a case of כתובה ketubah
because that's a much more serious language. Okay, now the גמרא's Gemara
going to say one minute, even in that case, it's not clear
that everybody agrees there's an obligation by a כתובה. ketubah. הניחא למאן
דאמר קבלן דכתובה אף על גב דלית ליה נכסים לבעל משתעבד שפיר.
hani nila l'man d'amar kablan d'ketubah af al gav d'leit lei nechasim
l'ba'al mishtabed, shapir.
That's good according to the opinion, which we'll see in a minute,
that says by קבלן kablan of a כתובה ketubah that even if
the husband has no money, it is the he is obligated. I'll
just finish reading this and then I'll explain it. אלא למאן דאמר
אית ליה משתעבד ואי לית ליה לא משתעבד מאי איכא למימר ela
l'man d'amar it lei mishtabed, ileit lei lo mishtabed, mai ika l'meimar?
But according to the position that even in a case of a
קבלן kablan by a כתובה, ketubah, he's only obligated if the husband
has money. He's not obligated if the husband doesn't have money. Now
that's a little bit bizarre, right? Because when is the biggest time
when you need a guarantee? When the actual person that you're hoping
to collect from doesn't have the money. That's when you're most insistent
on a guarantor. Here the גמרא Gemara says that when the person
doesn't have money, it might be that you are not obligated. How
is this possible?
So again, this goes back to the question of the דעת, da'at,
of the intent of the ערב. areiv. And if the husband doesn't
have money, then they're not going to get married if somebody can't
guarantee the כתובה. ketubah. So in that type of a case we
say the ערב areiv wasn't really serious about it. He was just
saying it in order should get the wedding to take place. Okay,
if the חתן chatan has money and nobody needed to be an
ערב areiv and you're stepping in to be an ערב, areiv, then
you are serious. So again, the sad part about this is is
that the more that the person is needed and the more that
this woman might be making a decision based on the fact that
there's a guarantor to the loan and she can't trust that she's
going to get it from the husband, then the more we say
that he might not really have גמר דעת g'mar da'at and he
might not really be obligating himself. Does not sound, I mean I
understand that we have to care about his גמר דעת, g'mar da'at,
but sounds like, you know, the woman is דוקא davka losing out
in the case where... It's most needed. But anyway, the גמרא Gemara
says even if we say that a קבלן kablan works for a
כתובה kesuva according to one opinion, that's only if the husband has
money. If the husband doesn't have money, a קבלן kablan doesn't work.
And here presumably the husband didn't have money, that was the story.
So how does the being of the קבלן kablan work in this
case? So the גמרא Gemara says like this: איבעית אימא מהוי הוי
ליה בשעת דהוה, Ibayis eima mihavi havilei bish'as d'ava, it's possible that
this רב הונא Rav Huna had money when they got married and
then the property got destroyed or depreciated. So
therefore the קבלן kablan really was obligating himself, the father, and that's
why it would have been possible to go collect because at the
time he really did have money, so the accepting to be a
קבלן kablan was serious. ואיבעית אימא אמלגבי בריה שיבודי משעבד נפשיה, V'ibayis
eima amalgabei brei shibudi mishabid nafshie, or here we're going to again
invoke the idea the father, that because he was the father, his
obligation he really did intend to obligate himself. Even though under normal
circumstance the guy just wants to get the wedding moving along, here
because the money is going to go, it is for the sake
of his son, actually his son's wife, but we feel that he
really is serious about wanting to put up the money. Okay, so
what the גמרא Gemara now has basically introduced is against our משנה
mishna that sounds that an ערב דכתובה areiv d'kesuva follows the normal
rules of an ערב, areiv, the גמרא Gemara has now said that
actually no, an ערב דכתובה areiv d'kesuva does not obligate himself and
even if somebody uses the language of a קבלן, kablan, even there
there's a debate and it might only be binding if it's a
case that the חתן chosson already has resources. So let's take a
look about how the גמרא Gemara continues with this question.
דאיתמר, D'itmar, because it was taught, here's the debate we were referencing
just now and let's actually now cite the original source of the
debate. ערב דכתובה, Areiv d'kesuva, if somebody agrees to be an ערב
areiv of a כתובה, kesuva, דברי הכל לא משתעבד, divrei hakol lo
mishtabeid, everybody agrees against our משנה mishna that you are not you
don't obligate yourself. קבלן דבעל חוב, Kablan d'baal chov, now if you
say you're going to be a קבלן kablan of a debt and
use the language of קבלן, kablan, דברי הכל משתעבד, divrei hakol mishtabeid,
then of course קבלן kablan is the stronger language and in a
case of a בעל חוב baal chov where money really is changing
hands and you're not just trying to get a couple married, everybody
agrees that the combination of those two definitely the obligation is binding.
So דברי הכל משתעבד. divrei hakol mishtabeid. קבלן דכתובה וערב דבעל חוב,
Kablan d'kesuva v'areiv d'baal chov, however if it's a mix, you use
the stronger language of קבלן kablan but it's a case of כתובה
kesuva where money isn't changing hands and maybe you're just trying to
get the wedding moving along, so maybe you're not really serious about
it, but you use the serious language of קבלן. kablan. Or you're
an ערב areiv and a בעל חוב, baal chov, you use the
lighter language of ערב areiv but it is a case of a
בעל חוב baal chov of really lending money where the guy is
putting out money because he's expecting to get it back. So in
those middle cases, it's a debate, פליגי, pligi, they debate. מר סבר
אי אית ליה נכסים ללוה משתעבד ואי לית ליה לא משתעבד, Mar
savar i is lei nechasim l'loveh mishtabeid v'i leis lei lo mishtabeid,
some say in those middle cases it only works if the לוה
loveh has money and then nobody was forcing the בעל חוב baal
chov to step, the ערב areiv to step up. And if he
stepped up anyway, then he's obligating himself. But if the לוה loveh
did not have money and nothing would have happened without him, so
he's just saying he's going to do it but he's not really
serious about it and he doesn't obligate himself. Again, now we're not
only not being fair to the woman, it's not being fair to
the creditor. I'm lending this guy money, he didn't have any money,
I was only going to do it because I was expecting to
get my money back. You agreed to do it and you said
you were going to be the ערב. areiv. But because,
so I'm only putting out money because I'm assuming I'm going to
be able to get it back because you said you were going
to be the ערב. areiv. But because you knew that I was
only going to do it for that reason, then you were just
saying it to get me to lend the money and you weren't
really serious. Like what? I mean that seems to be making absolutely
no sense that הלכה halakha should recognize your lack of גמירת דעת,
gemirat da'at, given that I am making decisions based on it. So
again, very hard to understand this גמרא. Gemara. Okay, but that's the
question. Some say in these middle cases it only is binding if
the person had money, so the ערב areiv doing it was not
necessary, so his doing it is a real obligation, but otherwise it
is not an obligation because he was just doing it to move
things along. ומר סבר, U'mar savar, and the other one holds, בין
אית ליה ובין לית ליה משתעבד, bein is lei bein leis lei
mishtabeid, that no,
regardless, even in these middle cases whether the guy has money or
doesn't have money, you said you were going to be a guarantor,
you are obligated. Now what's very strange here is a couple of
things besides the problems I've been flagging. One is who's the מר
mar and who's the מר? mar? This one holds this one, this
one holds that one. Nobody is named here. We're trying to finally
quote the source of this debate and we have absolutely no name
to position, no named אמורא. amora. So like the רבינו גרשום *Rabbeinu
Gershom* says or the רשב"ם *Rashbam* says that it was some אמוראים
*Amoraim* must have debated this, but we don't really even know who
was on which side of the debate. So that's very, very strange
about that,
about that. The other thing to note is that as against the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* we've been seeing earlier where the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
did have questions about the language of ערב arev, *arev* or the
language of קבלן *kablan* in terms of the order in which you
could collect, here it was actually debated whether an ערב arev *arev*
even for a loan had any obligation at all, not just a
question about the price like where you go to first. So very
strange the way this discussion seems to be like not fair to
the other side and against our משנה Mishnah *mishnah* and undercutting some
of the points that we said before and really limiting the situations
in which there's an assumption of liability, of obligation. Okay, but let's
see how the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* concludes.
והלכתא *Vehilchasa* the הלכה halacha *halakha* is, second wide line, ערב arev
*arev* when it's a case of ערב arev *arev* meaning of all
cases of ערב arev *arev*, whether you use language of ערב arev
*arev*, whether you use the language of קבלן *kablan*, בין אית ליה
בין לית ליה משתעבד *bein isle bein leisle mishtabed*. You know, the
person if you say you're going to be a guarantor, whatever language
you use, you're obligated. Okay, great, that's consistent with what we said
before. And the one so that's the saying the middle case is
yes, you are obligated. And the one thing that we are carving
out is the weaker language with כתובה *kesuva*, okay, which is except
for, בר מערב דכתובה *bar me'arev dekesuva*, except for when you use
the ערב arev *arev* language, the weaker language, and it's כתובה *kesuva*,
that is the one case that we are saying that you're not
really serious, and in that case let's see what we let's see,
דאף אגב דאית ליה לבעל לא משתעבד *de'af agav de'islei leba'al lo
mishtabed*. And in that case, when you used the ערב arev *arev*
language, even if the guy has money, because you're using the weaker
language, you're not really serious about assuming you are obligation. אף אגב
דאית ליה לבעל לא משתעבד *Af agav de'islei leba'al lo mishtabed*, מאי
טעמא *mai ta'ama*, מצוה הוא דעביד ולאו מידי חסריה *mitzvah hu de'avid
velav midi chasrei*. You're just doing a מצוה *mitzvah*, you know, you're
just trying to get this nice couple married and the woman nobody
is lending out money, the woman isn't lending out money, so you're
just signing on to do something nice and it's not really serious.
Now, it could be at this stage what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
means is that it was very pro-forma, you know, sort of like
we do the תנאים *tna'im*. It was more like a ritual of
signing on as the ערב *arev* and nobody took it seriously. If
that's true, it makes a lot more sense, you know, that it's
an honorific type of thing to sign on as the ערב *arev*,
but nobody ever really expected that to become a legal responsibility. I'm
not sure the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying that, but anyway, this
strange ruling that goes against what we've been saying before and does
not seem very fair, at least we are limiting it to the
one case of when you both use the weaker language ערב *arev*
and it's a case of כתובה *kesuva*, although we apply it regardless
of whether the guy has money or not. All right, now the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues. אמר רב הונא Rav Huna *Amar Rav Huna*,
says רב הונא Rav Huna *Rav Huna*, שכיב מרע shchiv mera שחילק
כל נכסיו ואמר מנה לפלוני בידי Mana l'ploni biyadi נאמן *Shechiv mera
shechilek kol nechasav ve'amar maneh leploni beyadi ne'eman*. חזקה אין אדם עושה
קנוניא על הקדש hekdesh, *Chazakah ein adam oseh kunya al hekdesh*. If
a שכיב מרע shchiv mera *shechiv mera*, somebody who's on his deathbed,
says, you know, gives all of his money to הקדש hekdesh. *hekdesh*,
gives all of his money to charity, but says, and then says,
but, you know, actually $100, 100 זוז *zuz*, I owe ראובן Reuven
*Reuven*. So then we believe him. So נאמן *ne'eman* he's believed. חזקה
אין אדם עושה קנוניא על הקדש hekdesh *Chazakah ein adam oseh kunya
al hekdesh*, right? We have a presumption,
we have, you know, we can take it for granted that you're
not going to try to cheat הקדש hekdesh. *hekdesh*. Oh, I want
ראובן Reuven *Reuven* to get the money, so even though it belongs
to הקדש hekdesh, *hekdesh*, I'll claim that I owe ראובן Reuven *Reuven*
the money. No, nobody's trying to cheat out הקדש hekdesh, *hekdesh*, so
you would be believed and the heirs would have to pay ראובן
Reuven *Reuven*. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says one minute.
מתקיף לה רב נחמן Rav Nachman, *Maskif la Rav Nachman*, so רב
נחמן *Rav Nachman* asked on this, וכי אדם עושה קנוניא על בניו
*vechi adam oseh kunya al banav*? But one minute, but the same
way a person wouldn't want to cheat out הקדש Hekdesh *hekdesh*, we
don't think a person would want to cheat out his children from
their inheritance? But ורב ושמואל אמרי תרוייהו *veRav ushmuel amri tavayhu*, but
רב *Rav* and שמואל *Shmuel* both say, שכיב מרע shchiv mera שאמר
מנה לפלוני mana leploni בידי *shechiv mera she'amar maneh leploni beyadi*, so
if on his deathbed somebody says I owe ראובן Reuven *Reuven* $100,
אמר תנו tnu, נותנין *amar tnu nosnin*, if he says and give
it to him, then we take him at his word and we
give ראובן Reuven *Reuven* the $100. לא אמר תנו tnu. אין נותנין
*lo amar tnu ein nosnin*. You don't give it to ראובן Reuven
*Reuven*. Why not? אלמא אדם עשוי שלא להשביע את בניו shelo lasbia
et banav *Almana adam asui shelo lehasbi'a es banav*.
So a person acts in a way to make it that his
you know, people shouldn't think his kids are rich. Oh, you know,
you died, you left your kids this big inheritance. So he's going
to make an announcement, no, I have plenty of debt, I have
a million dollars in debt to various people, so people won't now
go and try to cheat the kids out of their inheritance or
think, you know, the kids have all of this money. So unless
he says תנו tnu, *tnu*, he's not trying to. He's trying to
you know cheat his kids and give it to ראובן Reuven even
though ראובן Reuven doesn't deserve it, but he's still not serious when
he says it because he has another motivation. He's trying to make
it look that his kids are not rich. So if that's true,
how's that relevant here? So here the גמרא Gemara says as well,
הכא נמי hacha nami top of כ״ה ע״ב, kaf hey amud bet,
here as well,
אדם עשוי שלא להשביע את עצמו. adam asuy shelo lasbia et atzmo.
So you want to make yourself not look rich. So if you're
giving all of your money to הקדש, maybe you'll say, 'Oh, I
owe ראובן Reuven a million dollars,' so people don't think, 'Oh look
at this guy, he's so wealthy, he gave all of his money
to הקדש.' No, in order that people shouldn't think that, you're making
a claim that you owe a million dollars to ראובן Reuven and
unless you say תנו, tnu it's not serious. Now I have to
say this is hard to exactly understand. You understand why you don't
want to make your kids look rich and you're about to die
and people take advantage of them, so people should think that they
have all these outstanding debts. But here,
הקדש is going to get the money and you are about to
die. Why is it important that people think that you're not—don't look
rich? And nobody's going to try to take advantage of you in
your last few days or weeks or whatever because you've already just
gave all your money to הקדש. So I really don't—a lot of
these—the—today's דף, daf, I don't really understand. But that's what the גמרא
Gemara says. So therefore, maybe we should say the same thing that
we don't believe it's true unless you say תנו. tnu, So let's
see what the גמרא says. כי קאמר רב הונא התם דנקיט שטרא.
ki kamar rav huna hatam de-nakit shtara. No.
When רב הונא said that if you say, you know, 'I owe
ראובן Reuven a hundred dollars' after you've sanctified your property to הקדש,
you're believed, it's when ראובן Reuven has a שטר. shtar. Now you're
probably asking if ראובן Reuven has a שטר, shtar, why do I
need to say that I owe him the money?
So, you know, it might be that the שטר shtar isn't מקוים.
mekuyam. We'll see that in a minute. But תוספות Tosafot says that
one of the things going on here is that when somebody comes
to collect from orphans, even if he has a שטר shtar and
even if it's מקוים, mekuyam, he has to take a שבועה shvua
that he hasn't been paid because the orphans don't know the business
dealings of their father. So even though if somebody comes to me
with a שטר, shtar, right, I'm not believed to say that I
paid it because he has a שטר מקוים, shtar mekuyam, what's my
proof that I paid it? But if it's a case of orphans,
the guy—the guy even with the שטר shtar needs to make a
שבועה. shvua. But if the father on his deathbed said, 'I owe
the money,' then he doesn't need to make a שבועה. shvua. So
that's why since you already got the שטר, shtar, this person is
believed and it relieves the creditor of the need to make a
שבועה. shvua. So כי קאמר רב הונא התם דנקיט שטרא. ki kamar
rav huna hatam de-nakit shtara. So the גמרא says one minute, מכלל
דרב ושמואל דלא נקיט שטרא? michlal de-rav u-shmuel de-la nakit shtara? It's
when רב ושמואל Rav and Shmuel said that if a person says
he owes ראובן Reuven money and he doesn't say תנו, tnu, he's
not believed on his, you know, on his deathbed, right, that's a
case where ראובן Reuven doesn't have a שטר? shtar? But how could
that be? מכלל
דרב ושמואל דלא נקיט שטרא אמר תנו נותנין? michlal de-rav u-shmuel de-la
nakit shtara amar tnu notnin? So in that case if you would
say תנו tnu, you would give it, and if they're talking about
a scenario that the guy didn't have a שטר, shtar, but מלוה
על פה הוא, malveh al peh hu, with no שטר shtar it's
a loan, you know, it's a loan on oral loan, a loan
without a שטר, shtar, ואינה גובה לא מן היורשים ולא מן הלקוחות.
ve-einah gove lo min ha-yorshim ve-lo min ha-lekuchot. And the principle is
that on an oral—you know, a loan that doesn't have a שטר,
shtar, you cannot collect from the orphans or from, you know, buyers,
right, because there's no שיעבודא, shibudah, there's no lien. So if that's
true, right, we always have to be talking about a שטר. shtar.
Without a שטר, shtar,
nobody would ever collect from the orphans. So if the same way
רב הונא is talking about a שטר shtar and the guy is
believed and ראובן Reuven doesn't have to make a שבועה, shvua, so
in רב ושמואל Rav and Shmuel as well, the guy must have
a שטר shtar or else he wouldn't be able to collect from
orphans. So why isn't the person who said that he owed ראובן
Reuven the money believed when he says it on his deathbed? So
let's see what the גמרא says. אלא אמר רב נחמן, ella amar
rav nachman, says רב נחמן, אידי ואידי דנקיט שטרא. idi ve-idi de-nakit
shtara. Fine. Both of them, the case is that ראובן Reuven has
a שטר. shtar. ולא קשיא הא דמקוים הא דלא מקוים. ve-lo kashya
ha de-mekuyam ha de-lo mekuyam. In the case of,
you know, the first case of הקדש, ראובן Reuven has a שטר
shtar that is מקוים, mekuyam, that actually the signatures have been verified.
So there's—so the only thing left for is for ראובן Reuven to
have to make the שבועה shvua that it hasn't been paid. So
in that case if the guy on his deathbed said after he
was מקדיש makdish his property that 'I owe ראובן Reuven the money,
the debt is still outstanding,' even without the תנו, tnu. that alleviates—you
know, relieves ראובן Reuven of the responsibility to make the שבועה. shvua.
That's when he's already coming with a hundred percent ironclad שטר. shtar.
And then the guy saying it on his deathbed is enough. Okay.
הא דלא מקוים, ha de-lo mekuyam, but in the case of רב
ושמואל, Rav and Shmuel, ראובן's Reuven שטר shtar is not מקוים. mekuyam.
And in that case, you normally you would have—he would have to
establish—you know, be מקיים mekayem the signatures. So saying that—the fact that
the שכיב מרע shchiv mera said he owed the money does not—is
not enough to relieve from ראובן Reuven the obligation to be מקיים
mekayem the שטר. shtar. Only if you said תנו, tnu you know,
now you—then he says now
ראובן doesn't
have to be מקיים mekayem the שטר. shtar.
So we've come very far from the original statement that we just
trust a guy, he's not going to cheat הקדש etc. Now it's
like all of the evidence is already there. ראובן has the שטר,
shtar, you know, and it's מקויים. mikuyam. And the only point is
that if he says I owe him the money even without תנו,
tnu once it's already a שטר מקויים shtar mikuyam you don't have
to make a שבועה. shvua.
But if it wasn't a שטר מקויים shtar mikuyam you would have
to say תנו. tnu Without תנו tnu. not only do you have
to not without תנו tnu you have to be מקיים mekayem it,
okay, but with תנו tnu you don't have to be מקיים mekayem
it. That's what we now wind up saying. Not at all what
these earlier statements actually sounded like. I should also by the way
mention that as a matter of הלכה we actually פוסקין pasken that
even a מלווה על פה milve al peh can collect from יורשים.
yorshim. That was something that got established after the גמרא at the
time of the גאונים, Gaonim, and that allows you know for at
least people that have outstanding the creditors to not totally lose out
their money. All right, so that's important to know. All right, let's
continue. אמר רפרם, Amar Rafram,
הא דמקויים הא דלא מקויים. ha d'mikuyam ha d'lo mikuyam. אמר תנו
קיימי לשטריה. Amar tnu kimei lishtarei. So in a case of a
שטר אינו מקויים shtar eino mikuyam that's why the שכיב מרע shchiv
mera. had to say תנו. tnu. By saying תנו tnu it's effectively
a קיום kiyum of the שטר. shtar. לא אמר תנו לא קיימי
לשטריה. Lo amar tnu lo kimei lishtarei. But without it is not
a קיום kiyum of the שטר. shtar. All right, and even though
he says he owes the money, it's not enough, maybe he's doing
it שלא להשביע את בניו not to make his children look rich
and therefore קיום kiyum of a שטר shtar is still needed.
Fine. New point. אמר רבא Amar Rava said רבא. Rava. שכיב מרע
שאמר מנה לפלוני בידי ואמרו יתומים פרענו. Shchiv mera she'amar mana l'ploni
biyadi v'amru yesomim paranu. So שכיב מרע shchiv mera says I owe
ראובן money and the יתומים yesomim say yeah but we paid it
up. Now the question is it sounds very much like the previous
case and are we talking about with a שטר shtar because the
previous case we said we were talking about a שטר. shtar. So
here the ראשונים Rishonim explain that we are talking about a case
not necessarily whatever with the whole issue before on the same parameters
but we are talking about a case where the guy ראובן actually
demanded his money and the שכיב מרע shchivmera actually admitted it. Okay,
so that's like a different type of a scenario. All right, and
then afterwards the orphans said that we actually paid it up. ואמרו
יתומים פרענו אין נאמנין. V'amru yesomim paranu ein ne'emanin. I'm sorry did
I skip a line? אמר רבא שכיב מרע שאמר מנה לפלוני בידי
ואמרו יתומים פרענו. Amar Rava Shchiv mera she'amar mana l'ploni biyadi v'amru
yesomim paranu. So if he just says that
he if he just says that he
owes the money then the orphans are believed to say we paid
it up, okay, after the father died or the father paid after
he said it or whatever, נאמנין. ne'emanim. תנו מנה לפלוני Tnu mana
l'ploni but if he said give the hundred dollars to that
person ואמרו יתומים פרענו v'amru yesomim paranu and then they say we
paid it up אין נאמנין, ein ne'emanin, they're not believed. Now we
already know that the idea of תנו tnu more makes it clear
that the money is really owed when it's said by a שכיב
מרע. shchivmera? But the גמרא says but this distinction about their ability
to say we paid it up that doesn't make sense that that's
a function of whether he said תנו. tnu So the גמרא says
כלפי לייא klapi laya like where's this going? It's the opposite. איפכא
מסתברא, Ipcha mistabra, the opposite makes sense. אמר תנו מנה, Amar tnu
mana, if he says give the money כיון דפסקא אבון למילתא
kivan d'paska avun l'milsa since he made it very clear he commanded
them to give the money, איכא למימר דפרעי eika l'meimar d'parai then
it's more you can more assume they listened to him and they
paid it up, okay. מנה לפלוני בידי says I owe him a
hundred dollars and he didn't command them to give it, כיון דלא
פסקא אבון למילתא kivan d'lo paska avun l'milsa since he did not
exactly command the matter you know direct direct them, so איכא
למימר דלא פרעי eika l'meimar d'lo parai maybe they didn't pay them,
right? If anything it makes sense. Since you said that without the
תנו tnu
it's more questionable their obligation then they should be less believed to
say they paid. The more תנו tnu. is a stronger emphasis that
there exists an obligation and it's a stronger directive to them then
the more they then the more they should be believed that they
have paid. So because תנו tnu is stronger to establish the debt
and to create that directive they דווקא davka should be believed. Without
the תנו tnu they shouldn't be believed to say they paid. So
let's see what the גמרא says. אלא אי איתמר הכי איתמר. Ella
ee itmar hachi itmar. Fine, if it was said it was said
the following way, a little bit of the reverse.
שכיב מרע שאמר מנה לפלוני בידי ואמרו יתומים חזר ואמר לנו אבא
פרעתי נאמנין. Shchiv mera she'amar mana l'ploni biyadi v'amru yesomim hazar v'amar
lanu aba parati ne'emanim. If a שכיב מרע shchivmera says I owe
a guy a hundred dollars and he didn't say give it to
him and then the orphans say not we paid, okay, they say
oh afterwards our father told us that he had remembered you know
that he had paid, he had paid after he told us he
owed the money or he told us he had remembered afterwards that
he had paid. So in that case the father is the one
that says that I've paid
חזר ואמר אבא פרעתי hazar v'amar aba parati so in that
case נאמנין. ne'emanim. itkurei midkar אדכורי מידכר, itkurei midkar, itkurei midkar אדכורי
מידכר, itkurei midkar, tnu mana leploni תנו מנה לפלוני, tnu mana leploni,
tnu mana leploni תנו מנה לפלוני tnu mana leploni ve-amru yesomim chazar
ve-amar abba parati ואמרו
יתומים חזר
ואמר אבא פרעתי
ve-amru yesomim chazar ve-amar abba
parati but if he says give it and then he says
and then they say the father said that the father said that
he had already paid, in that case ein nemanim אין נאמנים, ein
nemanim, then they are not believed that the father said oh I
remembered that I already paid him. Why? De-im issa deparei lo hava
amar tnu דאם איתא דפרע לא הוה אמר תנו de-im issa deparei
lo hava amar tnu because and again it sounds like he's saying
the father didn't say afterwards he paid, the father said that after
he told us to give he remembered that he had already paid.
So in that case they're not believed because if he
really was uncertain he never would have been as black and white
as about saying tnu תנו. So again saying tnu תנו is an
absolutely more certain because it's more certain and more of a directive,
the orphans are not believed to say they paid excuse me because
it's more of a directive the orphans are believed to say they
acted on that directive and they paid, they would if it was
only saying that I owe the person they'd be less believed to
say they acted on that directive. So that's the case of when
the orphans are claiming it. But if now the orphans are claiming
not that they paid but our father remembered that he had already
paid, that's when then it reverses. Tnu תנו which is more of
an absolute debt and more of a directive the father wouldn't have
said that if he was uncertain. If he said mana leploni מנה
לפלוני it could be he was uncertain and then he remembered and
then he reversed himself. So let's just read that again so tnu
mana leploni ve-amru yesomim chazar ve-amar abba parati תנו מנה לפלוני ואמרו
יתומים חזר ואמר אבא פרעתי tnu mana leploni ve-amru yesomim chazar ve-amar
abba parati ein nemanim אין נאמנים. ein nemanim. If however they said
give if the father said give it and then they said the
father our father said oh I remember that I'd already paid it
off, in that case they're not believed de-im issa deparei lo hava
amar tnu דאם איתא דפרע לא הוה אמר תנו. de-im issa deparei
lo hava amar tnu. If he had really paid it's not possible
he would have said give given it he wouldn't have been mistaken
when he says give it means that he clearly absolutely remembered and
therefore they're not believed to say that he then afterwards realized he
had made a mistake. Okay so just to finish this up ba-ei
Rava בעי רבא, ba-ei Rava, Rava asked shchivmera she-hoda mahu שכיב מרע
שהודה מהו? shchivmera she-hoda mahu? So if a shchivmera שכיב מרע shchivmera
admits that he owes money to somebody somebody says you owe me
money and he says yes I do normally we say that that
admission is not binding is not binding in court unless he says
specifically you Reuven and Shimon be witnesses to see that I'm admitting
that I owe money otherwise he could just be saying it to
brush the guy off and we don't take it seriously but what
if it's a case of a shchivmera שכיב מרע? shchivmera So shchivmera
she-hoda mahu שכיב מרע שהודה מהו shchivmera she-hoda mahu tzarich lomar atem
eidai צריך לומר אתם עדי tzarich lomar atem eidai does he have
to say you be my witnesses and otherwise we say he's not
being serious o ein tzarich lomar atem eidai או אין צריך לומר
אתם עדי o ein tzarich lomar atem eidai does he not have
to? Tzarich she-yomar kitvu o ein tzarich lomar kitvu צריך שיאמר כתבו
או אין צריך לומר כתבו tzarich she-yomar kitvu o ein tzarich lomar
kitvu also can you write up an admission as a shtar שטר
shtar and turn it into a shtar שטר shtar normally you would
have to command the witnesses to say write it down as a
shtar שטר shtar but in the case of a shchivmera שכיב מרע
shchivmera do you have to do that or not? So the Gemara
says o ein tzarich lomar kitvu או אין צריך לומר כתבו o
ein tzarich lomar kitvu adam mishata beshaas misa אדם משטה בשעת מיתה
adam mishata beshaas misa o ein mishata beshaas misa או אין משטה
בשעת מיתה o ein mishata beshaas misa do we are we concerned
that a person would be like kidding around brushing the guy off
at the time of the death or do we assume if he's
a shchivmera שכיב מרע shchivmera and he's admitting it then he really
means it and we don't need him to do these to say
atem eidai אתם עדי? atem eidai? And the Gemara concludes basar de-ba-ei
hadar pashutei בתר דבעי הדר פשטיה basar de-ba-ei hadar pashutei after he
raised the question he came to the conclusion ein adam mashte beshaas
misa אין אדם משטה בשעת מיתה ein adam mashte beshaas misa a
person does not kid around at the time of death and if
he admits that he owes the money we take that as binding
and similarly divrei shchivmera keksuvim u-kmesurim dami דברי שכיב מרע ככתובים וכמסורים
דמי divrei shchivmera keksuvim u-kmesurim dami the same way we say that
when shchivmera שכיב מרע says something it's like it's written down and
it's like he did a kinyan קנין kinyan that means that a
shchivmera שכיב מרע words have greater weight and in a similar way
he does not have to give a specific directive to write the
shtar שטר shtar you can automatically write it as a shtar שטר.
shtar. Okay so that is the conclusion of some of these things
a shchivmera שכיב מרע does at the end where he admits that
he owes money. We'll just end with the Mishna and then finish
up the finish the masechet מסכת masechet tomorrow. Hamaleve chavero beshtar gove
minichasim meshubadim המלוה את חבירו בשטר גובה מנכסים משועבדים hamaleve chavero beshtar
gove minichasim meshubadim somebody lends money with a shtar שטר shtar that
creates a lien on properties this is things we've been assuming all
along and then he can go ahead and collect the property even
after it is sold to other people he can get collect from
encumbered property al yedei eidim gove minichasim bnei chorin על ידי עדים
גובה מנכסים בני חורין al yedei eidim gove minichasim bnei chorin however
if it's witnesses without a shtar שטר shtar that does not create
liens
and he only can collect from unencumbered property property that's in the
hands of the loveh לוה loveh and not property that has been
sold that's two points. Number one is that you need the shtar
שטר shtar to create the public nature of it and to create
the shibudim שעבודים shibudim maybe the shtar שטר shtar actually works to
actually be a form of a kinyan קנין kinyan to create the
liens but certainly the public nature and the other thing that it's
informing you is even though the shtar שטר shtar doesn't explicitly say
that there are liens we say achrayus taas sofer אחריות טעות סופר
achrayus taas sofer and those come automatically with the shtar שטר. shtar.
Hotzi alav ksavyado shehu top kof ayin hey הוציא עליו כתב ידו
שהוא Hotzi alav kesav yado shehu top קע"ה. הוציא עליו כתב ידו
שהוא top of קע"ה עמוד ב'. kuf ayin hey amud bais. הוציא
עליו כתב ידו שהוא חייב לו, Hotzi alav kesav yado shehu chayav
lo, גובה מנכסים בני חורין. goveh minechasim bnei chorin. If somebody takes
out a written IOU, I ראובן owe you שמעון Shimon a hundred
dollars, then that written
IOU can be used as evidence to make me if I'm ראובן
pay up, but it is not a public שטר shtar with witnesses,
so you cannot use it to collect encumbered property, you can only
use it to collect unencumbered property, property that has not been sold.
ערב היוצא לאחר חיתום שטרות, Arev hayotzeh leachar chitum shtaros, now let's
say after the שטר shtar has been signed, the guarantor put his
obligation on the שטר shtar underneath the signature of the witnesses. In
that case, גובה מנכסים בני חורין goveh minechasim bnei chorin the creditor
can if he's collecting from the ערב, can only collect from the
unencumbered property, but he does not have liens and he cannot collect
from property that the ערב has sold. Why is that? מעשה בא
Maaseh bo because he did it
after the witnesses signed, so it doesn't have the public nature that
comes through the signing of witnesses. So it was like it was
oral, it's like it was not in an official שטר shtar because
it did not have the witnesses sign after. If witnesses do sign
after, then it creates liens on the ערב's property. מעשה בא לפני
רבי ישמעאל ואמר גובה מנכסים בני חורין. Maaseh bo lifnei Rabbi Yishmael
veamar goveh minechasim bnei chorin. So a case like this came to
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael and רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael said fine, you
can collect from the property in the hands of the ערב but
not from property that he's sold. אמר לו בן ננס, Amar lo
Ben Nanos, בן ננס Ben Nanos said to him, אינו גובה לא
מנכסים משועבדים ולא מנכסים בני חורין. eino goveh lo minechasim meshubadim velo
minechasim bnei chorin. No,
in that case that he signed after the document was done and
after the loan was made, the ערב is completely off the hook.
You can't collect from the ערב at all. אמר לו למה, Amar
lo lamah, so רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael said to him why? אמר
לו הרי החונק את חברו בשוק. Amar lo harey achonek es chaveiro
bashuk. Let's say somebody was choking someone in the marketplace, ומצאו חברו
umatzao chaveiro and somebody saw what was happening, ואמר לו הנח לו,
veamar lo hanach lo, stop choking this guy, ואני אתן לך vaani
eten lacha and I'll give you a hundred dollars to stop choking
the guy. פטור, Patur, then you'd be exempt because he's obviously doesn't
really want to give the guy a hundred dollars, he's only trying
to protect him. שלא על מנת כן הלווהו Shelo al menas ken
hilveihu because it's not like I
said go, so now we're sort of translating it to the case
of the loan, when a person becomes a creditor an ערב after
the loan was made,
then the person who is lending the money is not doing it
on the promise of the creditor. And maybe the guy's only agreeing
to be a
creditor so I'm intervening after the loan and the money changed hands,
and I'm trying to get you to stop the מלוה malveh to
stop giving ראובן such a hard time and stop putting so much
pressure on. So I'm trying to do it to help out ראובן
from the
pressure that you're exerting on him, but I am not actually you
did not actually lend him money because of my promise. And therefore,
you cannot now come to me in order to get paid up.
Only when you take money out of your pocket partly because I
am guaranteeing the loan, that's when you're allowed to come to me.
שלא על מנת הלווהו. Shelo al menas hilveihu. אמונתו הלווהו. Emunaso hilveihu.
He did not lend him the money because of the trust that
he was having that he could collect. אלא איזהו ערב שהוא חייב,
Ela eizehu arev shehu chayav, what's the case of an ערב that's
obligated? הלווהו ואני נותן לך, Halveihu vaani oten lacha, lend him the
money and I will pay you. חייב, Chayav, then you're חייב, chayav,
שכן על אמונתו הלווהו. sheken al emunaso hilveihu. In that case, the
money was lent because I was believing, I put my hand in
my pocket and I lent the money because I was believing I
could come back to you. And that creates an obligation, not when
you come in later in the process. ואמר רבי ישמעאל Veamar Rabbi
Yishmael and now we end the last משנה in the last of
the בבות, Bavos, רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says, הרוצה שיחכים יעסוק בדיני
ממונות, harotzeh sheyachkim yaasok bedinei mamonus, someone who wants to be smart
should involve themselves in the learning
of civil law, דיני ממונות, dinei mamonus, שאין לך מקצוע בתורה יותר
מהן, she'ein lacha miktzoah batorah yoseir mehen, there is no field in
תורה Torah that is more demands more like intellectual capacity and sharpens
your mind more than the study of דיני ממונות. dinei mamonus. והן
כמעיין הנובע, vehein kemayan hanoveiah, they're like a flowing well, there's always
new ideas, והרוצה שיעסוק בדיני ממונות ישמש את שמעון בן ננס, veharotzeh
sheyaasok bedinei mamonus yishamesh es Shimon Ben Nanos, and if you want
to do
דיני ממונות dinei mamonus you should really
attend to שמעון בן ננס Shimon Ben Nanos because he really has
like a lot of not just book smarts but wisdom and he's
the one that you really want to learn with and from. Okay,
we will end with that now.